<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The briefe of the ministers bill for London tithe</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16779.10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838702</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838702</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 844:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The briefe of the ministers bill for London tithe</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The bill, requesting more equitable assessments, was read and rejected 21 March 1621--STC.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 16744.</note>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm as STC 16744.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (2 copies filmed).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3090:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The briefe of the Miniſters bill for London tithe.</head>
            <p>THe Citizens and inhabitants of the Citie of London and the Liberties thereof, are to pay their tithe by the Decree,<note place="margin">The Statute ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the 37. Hen. 8.</note> of euery x<hi rend="sup">s</hi> rent xvj <hi>ob. per annum,</hi> and of eu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry xx<hi rend="sup">s</hi> rent ij<hi rend="sup">s</hi> ix d. of all houſes, ſhops, ware-houſes, cellars, ſtable, &amp;c. without fraud or c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nin for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer.</p>
            <p>Contrary to the true meaning of the ſaid Decree, ſome defeat the M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſters of their tithe, by reſeruing their yearely rent or paiments,<note place="margin">The g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances.</note> by ſecret bonds, double leaſes (one with ſmall rent for the Parſon to demand his tithe; another for the Landlord, whereby he demandeth more rent:) others call their quarterly paiments by the name of Fines, Penſions, Incomes, New-yeares-gift, and many other ſecret contracts, reſeruations, and agreements, for auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of further charges to the Parſon.</p>
            <p>For reformation of theſe deuices and other grieuances, they moſt humbly intreate that commiſſions may be granted by the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper for the time being,<note place="margin">What the Mini<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s de<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re.</note> to the Lo: Biſhop of London &amp; his Chancellor, to the Lo: Maior of London &amp; the Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſome others, to aſſeſſe by valuation or otherwiſe, that ſome reaſonable tithe be paid of ſuch houſes aforenamed, as in their conſciences they ſhall thinke fit. Or that the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court of Parliament will be pleaſed to appoint any other order which in their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they ſhall thinke meete.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For many hundred yeares before the Decree,<note place="margin">Motiues.</note> houſes paid iij <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> v d. out of euery xx<hi rend="sup">s</hi> rent, as they were or could be let, or after a common valew; and houſes inhabited by the owners were to be valewed by the Church-wardens, by a compoſition betweene the Citizens and Miniſters. 17. Decemb. 1457.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The prices of all things are tripled ſince the Decree, and the Benefices within the walls not halfe ſo good, in reſpect of the loſſe of perſonall or priuie tithes, offerings to Saints, Church-lands, Obits, Mortuaries, and many other things, beſide the abatement of viij d. of euery xx<hi rend="sup">s</hi> rent of houſes, ſhops, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There be not ſo many poore Benefices of the like taxe in the Kings bookes in any ſhire of England, as are within the walls of London, ſome of them being taxed at 20. l. 30. l. 40. l. 60. l. 100 marks and more; by which their paiments are very great, for Subſidies, firſt fruites, continuall tenths, and other paiments.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Many Citizens, and ſome whole Pariſhes for the moſt part of the inhabitants therein, haue lately raiſed themſelues to a competent tithe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They deſire no houſe to be raiſed to more tithe then ſome Knights, country Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Citizens do already pay for houſes of the like worth in the Citie.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By this improuement, no one Benefice within the walls, ſhall come neare to that which hath bin lately raiſed in ſome one impropriation within the citie.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If there may be a reformation of ſome great houſes inhabited by the richer ſort, that pay by the forenamed deuices farre leſſe tithe then the meaner ſort of handicrafts men, the Miniſters may forbeare the poorer ſort of citizens, as hitherto they haue done, and ſtill deſire to do.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To auoide the ſuſpition of exceſſiue raiſing of the liuings in London, a prouiſo may paſſe, that if any Benefice ſhall be raiſed in tithe by valuing to 50 <hi>lib per annum,</hi> more then now it is at the making of this Act, then no Parſon or Vicar ſhall haue any more benefit by vertue of this Act.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Parſons and Vicars of London in time of ſuperſtition before the Decree, had reliefe from time to time by Conſtitutions, Compoſitions, Acts of Common councell, and Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>They moſt humbly intreat, that this moſt honorable Court would take to heart the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed eſtate of many poore and painfull Miniſters, that theſe variances being taken away, they may enioy peace with their people; in which happie ſucceſſe they ſhall euer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your honorable &amp; religious care, and not ceaſſe to pray that this Act, with many other ſuch like, may tend to your eternall comfort in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
